do
[Music]
so
hello everybody welcome to the 94th live
episode of ask abidjit
i hope you're doing well this fine
sunday evening good day good good
evening good night to all of you
wherever you are and let's see who all
is there i can see pankaj tyagi tejas
vinit migna
um
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you it's great to be
back on this live show
so today we're going to take questions
that you have asked in the comments so
let's get right into it right away
okay what's the first question the first
question is by rutuja
i'm aware that you're not really into
bollywood movies but i would like to
hear your thoughts on the kashmir files
and the genocide
of the kashmiri pundits
so i haven't seen the movie yet i have
had no time i would certainly like to
watch the movie i've heard it's a very
good movie the reviews are great the
attendance is great it's doing very well
so clearly it's being very well received
clearly it's a movie that
has struck an emotional
cord with the people of india
it is clearly a factual movie it does
represent it does seem to represent the
actual events as they happened
so i would certainly like to see the
movie so i cannot give you a review of
the movie because i haven't seen it yet
now what about the genocide of the
kashmiri pundits well that's uh
it's not something that happened
only
in 89 1991 it's something that's
happened in waves
and it is a continuation of a longer
process
the process
which culminated with the genocide of
the kashmiri pundits and their expulsion
from their homeland
that process began
about 1300 years ago with the genocide
in iran
so there was the arabic conquest of iran
the iranian iranian people the persian
people were zoroastrians mainly at the
time
right they were their culture and
civilization was closely
related to our civilization they the
persians are a daughter civilization of
india so they were conquered by the
arabs
and the first
uh cultural et et cetera genocide
happened there
so they were very quickly within a few
decades maybe two three decades they
were completely converted to the
religion of the arabs and whoever was
able whoever resisted i mean lots of
killings happened lots of persecution
happened many of these iranians the
persians they escaped and the only place
they could escape to was india and they
still live in india today india was
magnanimous enough to offer them refuge
in our country so our king our kings
local kings i think it was a king it was
a local king in gujarat who offered the
persians the parsis refuge and a place
to live in gujarat so that's why the
parcels still exist in india so the
first instance of this process happened
in persia the whole of persia within
just two three decades was completely
transformed the culture was wiped out
then
after some time after a few centuries
about a thousand years before today the
indian province the indian region of
gandhar
underwent the same process
terrifying atrocities terrifying
genocide it happened there in gandhara
we know that gandhara was a hindu and
buddhist place hinduism buddhism same
thing i've said that a hundred times
hinduism and buddhism are the same thing
different flavors of the same culture
and traditions the whole of central asia
was hindu and buddhist you will see
ruins of hindu temples and buddhist
stupas all across central asia what
happened there the same genocide
happened there the same thing happened
in gandhar which we now call afghanistan
there is no indian culture left there it
was india
i mean we know it from the mahabharata
times right gandhar
so what happened in kashmir in the in 89
1991 it happened first in iran then it
happened in central asia then it
happened in our own province of gandhar
and then
over the centuries there were these
these the turkic sultans who ruled water
over over kashmir
sikandar but chicken or something some
barbarian by that name a foreigner a
turk who committed untold atrocities
uh lots of people are massacred it was a
complete full-scale genocide and
then
in the in the late 1980s and 90s
that's when
the whatever was left was done
so there are very few kashmiri hindus
kashmiri pandits living in kashmir today
so that's the story
and this movie obviously it deals with
only what happened i i haven't seen it i
am assuming it deals with what happened
in 89 1991 when the
last expulsion and the genocide
last installment of the genocide was was
carried out
so i would certainly like to watch the
movie
and uh i would like to congratulate mr
vivek nihotri pallavi yoshiji etc for
making this movie this very important
movie it's being very well received and
i will certainly want to watch it maybe
in the coming week if i can find the
time but i will certainly watch it so
that's where what i can say
as of today without having seen the
movie i i know it's a very
uh it's not an easy movie to watch it's
very painful it's like shocking and all
but i think it's something that
everybody needs to go through so i will
certainly do that
okay vashi says that the current war
which is unfolding in ukraine has two
sides to it as most wars
uh there's a military one and the
political one the more prolonged the war
is going etc it's more it's going to get
more costly for russia
uh so the question is whether the u.s
has deliberately pushed putin into a war
as a trap where the political outcome is
always uncertain
to precipitate his downfall once he is
out of the picture once putin is out of
the picture the polarity of geopolitical
power may shift in back into the camp
of the us
so he's saying that uh so what she's
saying if if putin may win
although he may win militarily
if he cannot rally the russian and the
ukrainian people to his cause he's
doomed i disagree with that
uh it is of course see the the we have
to understand the character the nature
of the russian people the russian people
are accustomed to hardships
unfortunately it's a tragic land
look at the history of the past 1000
years
look at the great russian writers
tolstoy turganev and many of these
writers look at the stories they write
it's all tragedy it's all tragic the
whole russian history the ethos is
tragic
they have always had these powerful
rulers
tsars you know
uh nicholas the great
ivan the terrible uh catherine the great
and so on and so forth she was harina
sarina of course but the thing about
russia is this and then we had people
like stalin and so on the thing about
russia is this the people of russia will
tolerate hardship
but they will not tolerate failure
they will not tolerate a weak ruler and
mr putin is not a big ruler the people
of russia know what they are in for they
understand that that the west does not
consider them as equals the west wants
to see russia destroyed and fragmented
the people of russia understand this
russia is not a western nation
okay so uh
what the the people of russia will not
tolerate is failure military failure or
political failure
hardships they will tolerate they have
been accustomed to hardships for the
past 1000 years so that is not an issue
so uh i would not agree that he cannot
if he cannot rally the people to his
cause he is doomed if
all he has to do is he has to succeed he
has to succeed in his political and
military objectives the short-term
objectives of acquire of capturing
ukraine and whatever he intends to do
with the country and long term he has to
whatever else he's doing he needs to
pursue that and he has to succeed at
that and if you look at his track record
over the past 20 years he has been a
successful ruler and that is what the
russian people want they don't mind
hardships they even tolerated stalin but
they stalin was brutal
he did untold terrifying terrible things
on the russian people lots of people
unfortunately died as a result of his
policies
but at least he was successful and he
was able
see the thing that the ussr was able to
achieve
they took a broken country
a broken nation
and they built it into a superpower
within just a few decades
without
destroying the world without committing
genocide all over the world and without
plundering and looting the rest of the
world
the english-speaking people
who rule the world today
they were able to achieve the superpower
status by committing atrocities genocide
and plunder
on a global scale
the russians did it without
committing genocide and plunder and
destruction on a global scale
right they were able to industrialize
the country and uh
yes
there was a terrible holodomor the
terrible famine and they all all the
repression that stalin did in later
rulers also did and of course we know
that millions of people died as a
consequence of these policies some of
the policies were misguided some of them
were just terrible
but overall
from the big picture perspective the
nation became a superpower they they had
to pay a terrible price but they did not
make the rest of the world pay the price
for their rise so that is something even
the english-speaking world has not been
able to achieve to rise on its own
without destroying the world so that is
something they were able to do it and
the russians are rightfully justifiably
proud of what they were able to achieve
at that great cost
so they will not tolerate failure they
want success they will endure hardships
they are a hardy people now has the us
deliberately pushed putin into this war
as a trap of course they have
of course they have they
cornered
the us i'm sorry not the ussr it's kind
of interchangeable right these days so
they cornered russia they put russia
into a corner they slowly encircled
russia
see the americans have they always need
a big enemy
the americans need bad guys
if you don't have bad guys how will you
play the role of the global super cop
the global policeman so you if even if
there are no bad guys you need to invent
bad guys so they first uh
nurtured saddam hussein and then
suddenly all of all of a sudden they
painted him as a bad guy
they kind of
um encouraged him to invade kuwait
in uh
early 19th early in the early 90s 1990
or 1991 whatever there was and then that
painted him as a bad guy and so on so
forth so they need bad guys
so
putin
actually wanted to join nato but they
did not allow him to do that and they
slowly expanded nato eastwards they
encircled him they've placed nuclear
weapons in various countries like turkey
netherlands
other places as well
right to encircle russia
and then ukraine was the line that putin
could not allow them to cross because
that would be just uh it would it would
indicate it would signal to nato to the
u.s that we are powerless we we will
just we will allow you to just keep
going eastwards unchecked so they pushed
putin into a corner and they anticipated
of course they anticipated the americans
that eventually this eastward expansion
is going to lead to war
and they have used ukraine as the cannon
fodder for the war so the the people of
ukraine are suffering are paying the
price
for the american policies as it's always
been with various nations
so that's what's happening i don't see
mr putin uh falling
the americans need a few bad guys and
they would also not want mr putin
to uh to fall
so that's what is happening they have
certainly pushed him into a corner and
they
anticipated the reaction that they would
get from him and maybe they wanted it
maybe they want a completely bipolar
world which is what we are seeing
what's emerging right so yes so that
that thing i would certainly
agree with
riya says even if russia manages a
regime change in ukraine how likely is
it that the ukrainian people will accept
the new pro-russian regime and not
choose another pro-west regime taking
into account the rising negativity among
the masses against putin i don't see any
negativity rising among the masses if
you if you see the western media if you
see the indian media they will paint a
certain picture of the world
but that
doesn't reflect the exact accurate
reality
they are saying putin is losing the war
they have encircled the capital city of
kiev but they are still losing the war
apparently
if india and pakistan go to war india
captures large parts of pakistani
territory and encircles islamabad can
you claim that india is losing the war
and they are saying that lots of russian
people are demonstrating and protesting
against mr putin
where
so
these are fabrications created by the
media and various uh
think tank analysts and all that the
problem in india is that we are all we
only consume english speaking english
language news and that's why we are so
susceptible to fall to the propaganda
that emanates from the english-speaking
world from the west
our media simply parrots what they say
so that's why we get this feeling now
what about the ukrainian people will
they accept the new regime or not who
cares
the people
see my dear friends
let me introduce some realities of the
world to all of you
people don't matter
in the long run in the big picture it's
the rulers who decide and the people
have to accept what is done in the west
they call this democracy so you have
this cycle of voting every four years
every five years whatever and you
elect somebody and that person comes to
power comes to office but the person who
is in office is that person really in
power in the real sense who really
decides policy makes decisions
think about it
right so uh as far as russia is see
let's talk about ukraine will the people
of ukraine accept this regime of that
regime ukraine was part of the ussr for
how many decades
and did the people view of ukraine have
any say
in
whether they want to accept the ussr
regime or reject it
no
they simply
accepted it whatever was done they had
to accept look at china
do the people of tibet have any say
in who rules in beijing or whether they
want to accept the rule of beijing or
reject it they have no say in it do the
people of hong kong have any say in it
so please understand my friends whether
it's an autocratic country or whether it
is a country that looks like it's
democratic
it doesn't really matter people are easy
to manipulate through media through
entertainment through
various uh through government propaganda
and so on media is all propaganda please
understand this the bbc the bbc
is the propaganda arm of the uk
government
or the uk regime whoever is really
ruling the uk and understand this also
that the uk
is
a colony of the us
from the days of tony blair
the uk is nothing but a vasal state of
the us
the real
power the only power in europe is the
united states
so
you have this entire process the circus
of democracy and also it keeps the
people
happy but power is power and power
doesn't really care about democracy or
autocracy or anything power is the same
everywhere so it doesn't matter whether
the ukraine people you ukrainian people
like it or not you know what people like
people like stability people like peace
people like law and order people like a
good future for the children as long as
these things are provided in the right
signals and noises are made people are
happy
so that's how it's going to be as long
as mr putin succeeds and he's able to
stabilize ukraine and give the people of
ukraine long-term
a long-term good future they will
happily accept whatever is given to them
right
okay russia had warned nato that it
would take action on any country that
imposed a no-fly zone over ukraine what
is the meaning of no-fly zone and its
significance
what is a no-fly zone see anybody can
declare
a no-fly zone let's uh well to
understand this let's look at the map
because the map gives us a better idea
of
of what these things are
so
are you able to see it yes there you are
so this is the nation of ukraine ukraine
so
let me go to a different website for a
change
let's go to flight radar and and see how
things look
on flight radar
shall we do that
let's do it
so let's move out from india
and go eastwards
uh sorry westwards
so this
this website
shows you in real time
uh
the locations of most of the aircraft
that are flying around in the world and
what you see right here in europe
is you see this big gaping hole
over this region
which is ukraine
and east of ukraine there are flights
coming in and out of moscow and all
and some flights over over russia
but you can see a big gaping hole over
here in ukraine over ukraine and other
places so this is a de facto no-fly
no-fly zone it means that uh
aircraft commercial aircraft are
are not flying over this region now that
is voluntary they know there's a
conflict happening there and they don't
want to catch a stray missile with a
mind of its own so that's why all
commercial aircraft are staying away
from the region so that is voluntary it
is out of self-preservation now what is
an actual no-fly zone it is when a
country decides or declares
that over this whatever particular
geography nobody is allowed to fly
planes so that's when that's you what
you can do when you achieve air
superiority over a country so for
instance when uh
i believe that uh
when the americans invaded iraq
they had declared a no-fly zone over
iraq which means nobody was able to come
in
no plane was able was allowed
to enter the airspace over iraq without
explicit u.s military permission only
american military planes were allowed to
fly over this region
so that's a no-fly zone it means we
control the skies we will not allow
anybody without our express permission
to come to to enter this airspace that's
what it means so what does it mean when
a nation
imposes
or declares a no-fly zone it is not
enough to declare it you have to enforce
it so ukraine is right now uh
controlled more or less by russia right
and we know that they have achieved air
superiority over ukraine in the first
few hours of the war
so
okay let's not go to kharkiv
so that's what we know now if the
americans were to declare a no-fly zone
over ukraine it would mean that they
would say nobody is allowed no plane is
allowed to enter the ukrainian airspace
without american permission
but ukraine
the airspace is already controlled by
russia so if the americans declare a
no-fly zone it is essentially they are
contesting
the russian dominance
in ukrainian airspace
and they are telling russia that you can
your planes cannot uh enter ukraine
without all permission
but russia already has
uh air control air superiority in
ukraine so to enforce
this no-fly zone the americans would
have would actually need to take
military action
to enforce it which means they would
have to send their fighter planes
and
engage in aerial battles with the
russians with the russian air force
so that means you are actually going to
war with russia
to declare a no-fly zone and then not be
able to enforce it would indicate that
you are toothless and you are powerless
so no country will declare a no-fly zone
without being able to enforce it and the
americans if they enter into a conflict
with the russians it could escalate
beyond anybody's imagination so it is
not something they want to do it's not
something anybody wants it could lead to
a wider escalation of the conflict
the americans and russians have not
fought for decades
and if if a
shooting match begins it may go to any
extent it could even lead to nuclear war
so that's why the americans are not in a
position
to uh to enforce to to declare and
enforce the no-fly zone and the russians
have made it very clear that we will not
tolerate such a thing you try to do it
we're gonna shoot you down
so
right now that's not gonna happen the
americans know that that is a line they
cannot cross because that would lead to
a much wider escalation of the war it
would essentially lead it could very
likely lead to a much wider escalation
of this war and
and many more countries could could get
involved which
essentially is saying we are
precipitating a third world war which is
something nobody wants
right next question
oh my god what on earth is this help
okay so let's see what this says lots
and lots of wonderful people are saying
brahmos is not nuclear capable contrary
to what people think brahmos is not
nuclear capable missile brahmos is not
nuclear powered brahmos is not nuclear
capable brahmos is not nuclear-capable
missile according to mtcr rules blah
blah blah blah blah
zeta leadership says brahmos is not
designed to carry nuclear warheads and
so both is saying again this is not
nuclear capable and mtcr laws and all
that whatever
so this is just a small sample of the
number of comments i've received saying
that you are wrong brahmos is not a
nuclear-capable missile array baba
where do you get this information from
my dear friends
in what world are you living is it
coming from your favorite youtuber or
your favorite uh
media channel who's telling you that the
brahmos is not nuclear capable let me
let me i mean let me show you something
so please take a look at this
what does it say this is the
very
famous portal called the national
interest it's an american website
what does it say here india's sukhoi 30
fighters now come with nuclear brahmos
missiles so what does it say that
brahmos is a nuclear missile it's a
nuclear-capable missile let's see one
more
so this is uh
militarytoday.com
it says the brahmos cruise missile can
carry nuclear warheads let's see even
more
this is the time now news
more power to the indian air force's
nuclear capable brahmos has successfully
test fired from sukhoi 30 mki of the bay
of bengal i can show you 500 more
examples
that corroborate what i am saying the
brahmos is a nuclear-capable cruise
missile it's a supersonic movement
cruise missile i don't know where people
get this information from please learn
how to search for authentic information
some
news portal somewhere says the brahmos
is not nuclear capable or maybe
wikipedia says it i don't know who says
it
why do you believe that can't you look
at different sources of information more
reliable sources of information the
brahmos is a nuclear-capable missile
and then they're talking about the mtcr
rules
according to international law mtcr mr
whatever india is a member so india is
not allowed to do this do that
the pakistanis are also bound by the
mtcr the chinese are also bound by the
mtcr so how did pakistan acquire
ballistic missile technology via china
from north korea what happened to the
mtcr rules misha missile technology
control regime
why does it only selectively apply to
india
i just don't agree the this sheep
sheep-like behavior that we have to
follow international law no we have to
follow nothing we have to do what is in
our best interest
so the mtcr said this and that see what
is the mtcr the missile technology
control regime and according to this
this
it's a gang
and they these are the countries that
have that are the powerful countries
india was not a member of the mtcr
and because of that india was not
allowed to receive missile technology
from a third country like russia for
instance
which
in which the missile would have a range
of more than 300 kilometers that's why
the initial brahmos was said to have a
range of 290 kilometers
all right
well the thing is very simple you change
the fuel your range will change
so if you have a missile that has a
stated range of 290 kilometers but you
change the fuel in the ram jet engine or
wherever else in the other engine in the
initial engine you may have a different
range which may be less which may be
more
so
the initial
version the block one i think it's
called the block one ramos was said to
have a range of 290 kilometers but there
were
well
there were
rumors you could say that you could call
them that this missile could go much
further than that then india in 20
whatever a few years ago became a member
of the mtcr regime and then india now
can acquire technology or export
technology to mtcr members
in which the missiles have a longer
range there is no limitation to that
so newer versions of the brahmos i
believe they have a range of 700
kilometers 800 kilometers 900 kilometers
uh we are supposedly building uh
developing a more advanced version of
the brahmos with
a range of more than 1500 kilometers
right
there is the brahmos new generation
missile which is a lighter and shorter
missile
uh then there is the aerial brahmos
missile which can be launched from the
sukhoi aircraft and maybe the rafale
also then there is a brahmos-2 missile
that's been developed which is not a
supersonic missile it's a hypersonic
missile which will have a very long
range maybe more than 1500 kilometers so
the our regular brahmos has a
has a ramjet engine it is it's a
two-stage missile the first stage is i
think it's a solid fuel stage
which accelerates the missile to mach 1
which is approximately the speed of the
speed of sound
and once the missile crosses mach 1
that's when you can ignite the ram jet
because the ramjet needs supersonic
speeds so the the that's when the ram
jet engine is ignited the first stage is
jettisoned and that's when the missile
goes way beyond mach 2 it reaches nearly
mach 3 which is
three times the speed of sound so that
is the brahmos the regular brahmos
missile brahmos 2 which will not have a
ramjet but a scramjet which is a
supersonic combusting ramjet engine
the new brahmos the brahmos 2 will have
will have a
top velocity of about mach 8
which is eight times the speed of sound
so it's it is a
hypersonic missile so i don't know
whether it's been developed with whether
it is still under development we will
not make these things very clear
obviously we should not but the thing is
this these missiles can carry
conventional warheads
they can carry rocks if you want if you
want to increase the kinetic energy of
the impact
if you want to cut a ship in in half
then you don't need to carry a warhead
you can just put 200 tons of 200 kilos
300 kilos whatever whatever the weight
is of rocks
or or concrete just to increase the
kinetic energy of the impact you can do
that the brahmos can destroy a ship
without carrying a warhead
or you can even put a nuclear warhead in
the brahmos so it's up to you what you
want to do is if you own the missile if
you have it and we we own the missile
india right so the brahmos is 100 a
nuclear capable missile i don't know
where you get this misinformation for
from it's clear that this misinformation
is very widespread lots i mean dozens of
people have made this comments which is
completely incorrect
okay
next uh
oh joshua says can pakistan re-engineer
the brahmos missile or give it to the
chinese to re-engineer on their behalf
because china will want to arm pakistan
as much as possible to pressurize etc
all that
the brahmos missile okay we are assuming
the missile that entered pakistan and
crashed in pakistan was a brahmos it
does look like it was that
so
and there is some debris that's
available well what you have
is a missile that is completely
destroyed
it's like we like we know it's a
supersonic missile it travels at nearly
three times the speed of sound what is
the speed of sound
333 meters per second
three times the speed of sound is
a kilometer per second it is literally
faster than a bullet
that's how fast this enormous missile
flies
when it crashes somewhere do you think
you will retrieve anything that can
be salvageable or will make any sense to
you from a re-engineering reverse
engineering perspective no
all you will
be able to recover after the explosion
the crash is mangled bits and pieces of
metal
you cannot reverse engineer anything
from that
not the engine
you may get some traces of fuel you may
be able to determine what fuel they are
using that's what you will be able to do
the engine will be destroyed beyond
recognition
the initial engine will not even be
there because that's the first stage
which accelerates the missile to mach 1
and beyond and then you have the ramjet
which takes it to mach 3. the ram jet
will be totally destroyed
whatever electronics are within will be
vaporized so you will get nothing that
you can actually use
and and make any sense off and it's not
like the missile uses any special
materials it's just regular steel i
believe it's a heavy duty missile
there is no attempt to
minimize
the
weight of the missile which means that
you they would use regular steel as far
as i know so there is nothing that they
can really reverse engineer and the
chinese already have
a
certain version
of a russian missile of the onix 800
missile
which was used as a template for the
brahmos so the chinese have a version of
the older missile which is in some ways
similar to the brahmos
or a previous an older
generation version of the brahmos
so i i don't think the chinese would
even need or want to reverse engineer it
of course there are certain things that
they would want to learn but they won't
they will not be able to retrieve
anything of any value from the mangled
wreckage of that one missile i mean you
would not send a missile into enemy
territory if there was something that
they would be able to retrieve from it
right and
lots of people are telling are saying in
the comments that this was deliberately
this this was definitely a malfunction
india did not send it deliberately
grow up please
you don't send a nuclear missile
a nuclear-capable missile even an
unarmed supersonic missile into enemy
territory by mistake there is a whole
sequence of steps that needs to take
place before a missile launches
and these missiles are
very carefully guarded
it's not like some sweeper is allowed to
go and press a button and the missile
takes off it doesn't happen like that
there's a whole sequence there's a whole
chain of command multiple people have to
sign off on the
launch process
well that's how it goes in case you
don't know so this i do not see this as
a as an accidental launch
right we can say it's an accidental
launch because that's how you should
make it look
you should not be you know you cannot
tell the world we did a deliberate
launch so that's why you call it an
accidental launch i do not
see it as an accidental launch
so uh i don't think there is anything
that the brahmos that the pakistanis or
the chinese would be able to reverse
engineer from our missile
vishal says russia is made up of many
republic sahara republic etc and federal
subjects similarly china has five
autonomous regions guangxi xinjiang
tibet ningxia inner mongolia could you
please tell what level of power what
level of power do these administrative
divisions hold
are they just like local governments or
do they have some control over the
decision making for their region let's
take a look at a
chinese
administrative
divisions
let's take a look at that and let me
share that with you
let me share that image
so i'm just doing a google search a
simple google search for that
and let's take a look at this
maybe this
so there are certain so-called
administrative divisions of china
xinjiang
tibet
so some of these are so called
autonomous regions and some of these are
provinces and so on the question and
similarly we have something similar
for russia every country has internal
administrative divisions
you can call them whatever you want to
call them in india we call them states
and union territories in china they call
them provinces in pakistan also i
believe they call them provinces in
russia they call them whatever else
the nomenclature doesn't matter so the
question is
how much power do these administrative
divisions hold
which means that if you have a local
government in let's say tibet or
xinjiang or king high or sichuan or
unanimous whatever how much power does
the local administration have
and similarly for russia the answer is
uh i would say very simple they have
very little real power
in a country like china which is a
one-party state
china is
is essentially
an imperial system
they can call it whatever they want to
call it the chairman of the chinese
communist party
who doubles up as the president of the
country which is mr xi jinping
and then you have local administrative
local governors for each province and
and
autonomous region
the power in a country which has an
imperial system is always concentrated
at the center
the imperial throne beijing
so the majority the majority 99 of the
power in the country
lies within the inner core of the
chinese communist party the politburo or
the
or the four or five
most powerful people and among them the
first among equals is obviously the
chairman xi jinping so all these
autonomous regions etc they have next to
no power they just simply do what they
are told
and similarly for russia also you have
governors etc of all the various
provinces oblasts and whatever they're
called
they answer to mr putin
they get their funding from the center
from from the kremlin
and they are completely dependent on
everything on the kremlin
so they have to perform they have to
carry out the orders they have to carry
out whatever they're told if they keep
doing it they stay in power
otherwise the governor is replaced and
somebody else is put in place and their
only job is to follow our orders there
is no
democracy or any such thing yeah you
have voting and all and so on so forth
but you know that's not really how power
works anywhere in the world even in
so-called democratic countries
even in india
all right
so
that's how it is
so these local governments have very
little control over decision making they
simply follow orders obviously they will
be allowed to
make some decisions
and as long as the law and order is is
preserved and the the
overall policy is followed you can do
whatever else you see fit to keep things
running smoothly so that's the level of
power they have
rishi says you once said on the ranvir
show that china's stable political
system gives them an edge over india and
political instability in india is
stopping us from being bringing out our
full potential how can we achieve that
kind of stability in a democracy like
india answer is very simple you cannot
have that sort of stability in a
democratic system in a true democracy in
a true democracy it is the mob that
rules it is the will and and
the whims of the mob of the people that
decide the fate of the country and as
long as you have a system in which there
is the cyclic
uh
cycle of elections every four years or
five years we have five year systems in
india
and
then you will
then the problem is that the leaders
whoever comes to power their main focus
will always be on the next elections
because unless you are in power you
cannot do anything for the country so
even if your intentions are good even if
you want to do contribute something good
to the country you have to keep on
making compromises to keep the people
happy because you have to be re-elected
so it's a constant cycle in india
if you look at the news media whatever
your favorite channel is their favorite
topic is politics politics politics
politics that's all there is india is
obsessed with politics there's always
some election somewhere and just imagine
the amount of energy
of the state machinery of the of the
government government machinery and the
amount of money that is
utilized in this is in running these
elections my goodness
and
you never know what's going to happen in
election you may have a good chief
minister a good prime minister gone when
the election results are out
so it's a very unstable system and
especially when you have a parliamentary
democracy when the people cannot
directly elect the prime minister or the
chief minister you can only elect your
local representative and then these
local representatives will get together
an elected leader among their own why do
we have such a system why can't we have
a direct system in which we can elect
a prime minister president whoever it is
and that person gets stable five-year
term why can't we have that we don't
have that so this is a system that is
designed to be unstable and then if you
have a hung parliament then you will
have a coalition government which by
definition is an extremely weak and
unstable government so this system that
we have is by design
unstable
it keeps on
it it forces even good politicians even
good leaders to keep on
doing these populist measures keeping
the people happy giving them
reservations giving them freebies
and so on so forth so that is what is
holding the country back
the chinese have an imperial system you
can call it whatever you want it's an
imperial system the way empires have
been run for thousands of years so
that's what they have they have no need
to appease the public the uh the public
is expected to quietly obey what they
are told to do that's how it works in
china right so there is no need to
appease the public there is no need to
stand for election so the system is very
stable they can have 10 year plans 20
airplanes 100 year plans and they will
keep following the plan no matter what
leader leader is currently at the top in
the chinese communist party and they
have a very
harsh cut throat system in the chinese
communist party the the the
the leader who can
or the people who come to power are the
people who have been able to
defeat everybody else within the
within the ranks of the chinese
communist party only the hardest of the
lot can rise to the top
so
by design the system is such that you
will have very strong leadership
centralized leadership
and stable leadership so that is what is
the difference between india and china
so this system which is by design
unstable is what is stopping india from
achieving its full potential i am not
saying that india should
uh should
take up
uh an autocratic system a dictatorial
system
what we can do is we can have a
different form of democracy may be a
presidential form of democracy that is
again democracy
but at least you are guaranteed
stability on a five-year cycle
so let's say you are electing a
president who doesn't need the support
of so so and so numbers of members of
parliament the people elect a president
directly and once a president is elected
to power that person he or she has a
guaranteed five-year term
so if you have that sort of system which
is still a democratic system then you
are guaranteed
way more stability than we have today so
there are things that certainly need to
change in india
so there is something we could learn
from china i'm not saying we should go
full autocracy and full dictatorship no
we can have a better democratic system
india is the birthplace of democracy
look back at what worked for us in the
past and we can draw inspiration for
that from that
in the 21st century
okay um
r73 is elected it's a missile isn't it
okay so he says i disagree with the
point that two powerful countries with a
long shared border will come to conflict
that's a myopic one-dimensional
view of the world in a multi-dimensional
world for example
canada and u.s are two very powerful
countries saudi arabia and uae are very
powerful countries turkey and greece are
all very powerful countries all fall in
the same category but i haven't seen a
single bullet fired in the last 7 200
years
dear sir
welcome to this universe i i assume you
have come from a parallel universe in
which a different
different system exists
so maybe in
i don't mean to be disrespectful i'm
just trying to be humorous
maybe in a parallel universe canada is a
powerful country
maybe in a power in a parallel universe
saudi arabia and uae tiny microscopic
uae is a powerful country
and maybe in a parallel universe turkey
and greece are powerful countries
let me explain something my friends
let's let's let's go to the map and let
me explain
um
so the map is the best way to look at
geopolitics to understand geopolitics
so you are saying that canada is a
powerful country
let me share a piece of news that came
in just a couple of days ago
uh
this powerful country
so this is news look here
this is uh what this this lady is
canada's defense minister her name is
anita anand she's of indian origin so so
trudeau's defense minister announced to
canadians that canada has exhausted
inventory from the canadian armed forces
and they are there are capacity issues
after sending all of our equipment to
ukraine's president
which means
to translate that it means that canada
has run out of arms and ammunition
whatever little they had they have given
to ukraine
is that your definition of a powerful
country
look at north america there is only one
powerful country in north america
which is the united states the other two
countries in north america canada and
mexico are vassal states of the united
states all the countries in south
america are also under the same
situation there is only one power in the
americas one undisputed power that does
not tolerate any other power that is the
united states canada is not a powerful
country canada is a colony of the us
please understand that canada is by no
definition a powerful country
let's say saudi arabia and uae
saudi arabia is a u.s colony
saudi arabia is a u.s vassal state so is
the uae
in by what definition are they a
powerful are these powerful countries i
don't understand that
maybe you have not been
maybe you are new to this channel so you
may not have been listening to what i've
been saying let's talk about turkey and
greece
turkey
is a member of nato which makes it a u.s
fossil state turkey has u.s nuclear
weapons on its soil when you have a
superpowers military
equipment on your soil on a permanent
basis it means you are a vasal state of
that country so how does it make turkey
a powerful nation yeah sure they have a
powerful military
and they do it
indulge in various military adventures
from time to time they can do it only
with the explicit approval of the united
states and when you say that they have
not fired a single bullet in the last 60
70 200 years are you not aware of the
situation in cyprus in 1974 turkey
invaded cyprus
and took over the northern one-third
plus of the country cyprus used to
belong to greece so turkey and greece
went to war greece is a completely
powerless country greece is not even a
small power
and please understand this also
there is only one power in europe it is
not the european union
it is not nato it is not germany which
is the most advanced country it's not
france
the only
genuine power in europe is the united
states
and the united states has ensured that
europe remains peaceful more or less and
stable
after 1945.
until now
right of course the you had the yugoslav
civil war and some things here and there
you had
a civil war in spain and you had various
things you had the
troubles in ireland but those were low
scale small scale conflicts
so the only real power
in europe is the us
turkey is not a powerful country greece
is not a powerful country all the
examples you have given are not of
powerful countries it may look like they
are but they are not welcome to the real
world sir
so that is what i can offer you and i
hope you will
try and
view the world
through what power really is what
is power
most people don't understand what power
is
power is
is something that is uh well hard to see
if you don't know where to look okay
let's go to the next country next
question dhruv says in your podcast you
always say india needs a strong leader
for at least 50 to 50 to 20 years and i
always feel that somewhere this is
against the principles of democracy
sometimes the leader chosen by the
masses could not be a strong leader but
a person who can influence people easily
so do you believe democracy is the best
practice for a country like india with
so much diversity and is there any other
kind of system that could work better in
the case of india according to you
listen
india is the
birthplace of democracy we have had
democracy in india for thousands of
years not your western style democracy
which is a fake democracy we had
democracy for thousands of years have
you heard of the mahajanapadas these
were democratic republics
you had elected kings
but you had kings yes so it's a hybrid
system it's an indian system it's the
way it works in india the principles of
democracy i have no interest in whatever
principles people talk about
of democracy what is more important the
long-term
national interest the long-term security
stability and prosperity of the country
or some vague principles of democracy
who cares
it doesn't matter what system you use it
doesn't matter whether the cat is black
or white as long as it catches mice what
is important
is the long-term security prosperity
in progress
stability of the country that is the
only thing that matters
it doesn't matter whether you have a
dictator in power whether you have a
democratically elected president prime
minister whatever in power or if you
have a king or an emperor in power
what the only thing that matters is the
long-term
national interest the long-term security
stability and prosperity of the country
and its people that's the only thing
that matters i don't care about any
principles of democracy or dictatorship
or imperial system or anything it
doesn't matter what system is there
the people must prosper the country must
prosper the country must remain safe and
secure and stable over a long period of
time centuries i'm talking about that's
what matters
who cares what system is there
right so i think
the current form of the current system
that we have in india is is terribly
unsuited for the country
we need to have we need to go back to
our own past i'm not saying we need to
have an emperor or a king i'm not saying
we need to have a dictator i saying that
we need to have our own we need to
revive our own form of democracy
that's what we need to do
and to ensure that there is security
stability and prosperity in the long run
over a time span of decades and century
centuries right so i
so you can have that with within a
democratic system for sure i have always
said that i i believe in democracy i
believe that the people are the ultimate
arbiters of their own fate
but
then so so we need to have the right
system that's what i'm saying the
it doesn't matter which system it is
there what could work better for india
any system that gives us stability
and these in these things long-term
national interest any system like that
is fine for me i don't care
what do you think was the main cause of
the american invasion in vietnam apart
from their baseless reason reasons of
demilitarizing the area
was it the capturing a resourceful area
or some geopolitical reasons as china
wasn't a threat for them in that period
of time okay so the vietnam war is a
very drawn out protracted thing you can
have
a six-month course on what happened in
vietnam right
uh so i'm gonna have to answer this in
five minutes so i'll i'm gonna make it
short
so uh
before the second world war when did the
second world war begin 1939 i believe
and it went on until 1945. so before the
second world war
vietnam was a colony of france
where is vietnam you know where india is
yes go eastwards eastwards eastwoods and
you come
to southeast asia and here is vietnam
it's a strange shaped country a long
country from here north vietnam hanoi
all the way down south to saigon or ho
chi minh city right it's kind of like
chile that's sort of geography
so
before the second world war
vietnam was a french colony even today
you will find that french culture and
french language has a certain status
high status in vietnam even today
so vietnam was a french colony
in the second world war in that period
it was occupied by the japanese imperial
forces
japan rampaged across all of asia it
came to the
doorstep of india it entered manipur as
well we had the battle of infall and
battle of kohima and so on
in which the ina was also involved which
is a different story so the the the
vietnamese were first under the french
then they were occupied by japan
after the second world war after the
defeat of japan
uh
during the second world war during the
invasion during the occupation by japan
the viet minh
was a resistance
force
it was a vietnamese communist
resistance force
and their leader was ho chi minh
so after the japanese were defeated the
uh
the viet minh were able to capture power
in northern vietnam
and the french were able to retain power
in southern vietnam right so the country
was basically uh divided into two and
then there was some kind of an agreement
in geneva i believe in the mid 50s early
50s or somewhere i don't remember the
dates look it up look it up please
so there was this agreement in geneva
which was
obviously broken by the europeans it's
always this colonial attitude so vietnam
was officially divided into north
vietnam and south vietnam and they said
there would be elections and then the
country would be unified the elections
never happened
so north vietnam was run
by ho chi minh by the communists and
south vietnam had a so-called democracy
in south vietnam we had there was this
leader
this uh ruler i forget his name
but he was
unpopular deeply unpopular
he was
very much mentally colonized he
oppressed the buddhists who the buddhism
is buddhism and hinduism were
historically the main religions of
vietnam now it's mostly buddhism
so uh this guy
who i forget his name but he was
oppressing the buddhists he was
promoting christianity there was this
very sad unfamous tragic incident of a
buddhist monk who
set himself on fire it was captured by
on on camera the the very iconic images
so he did that the self-immolation in
protest against the persecution of the
native religion and culture of vietnam
and the imposition of christianity so
the guy who was ruling south vietnam was
very deeply unpopular then there was a
coup he was expelled and somebody else
was put in place but
the but the government remained
unpopular and the north vietnamese
wanted to
to reunify the country and their leader
was ho chi minh
and then so there was this state of
civil war which which kind of began and
the americans were very very of this
so the americans had seen what happened
in europe
the ussr became a major power and then
many of these eastern european countries
became communist countries
so they saw that communism was liable to
spread like this they called it the
domino effect you also had the same
thing in korea
korea also was divided into two north
korea and south korea
and north korea was under chinese
influence and it was a communist regime
it was a dictatorial regime so the same
situation was there in korea as well so
the americans got involved they sent
their so-called
political advisors or military advisors
were what it was whatever it was called
thousands of them maybe more than 10 000
of them
and then they decided to get involved
militarily to defeat the communists
right so the main cause of the u.s
invasion
in vietnam well they said it is to
defeat communism because communism is
liable to spread it has this domino
effect and they did not want the whole
world to become communists because they
believed in democracy in western liberal
values and human rights etc
right
so then they
they did this false flag incident in the
gulf of tonkin
the so-called gulf of tonkin incident in
which a u.s naval ship was attacked
apparently by north vietnamese
boats or missile boats or whatever it
was
torpedo boats
and then they took that as the pretext
for starting the war they said they the
vietnamese have attacked us
attacked us and this gives us a just
cause to go to war and that's how the
whole
business of the vietnam war began the
vietnamese don't call it the vietnam war
they called the american war but we
because we are all part of the western
world we are part of the
english-speaking world we are mentally
colonized so that's that's why we in
india call it the vietnam war it's
actually the american war the americans
initiated the war and they lost they
lost terribly in the north vietnam was
one and they were able to reunify the
country
and then vietnam became a communist
country of sorts
today also it is well
officially a communist country but they
have
uh they have been able to
develop the economy quite well and they
are doing reasonably well they are doing
there they are reasonably reasonably
mildly populous country the living
standards are higher today in vietnam
than in india today right so it's doing
well
so that is the story of the vietnam war
in very brief i have left out lots of
stuff but
because of the format of this show
next
akash says i wonder if the relevance of
the question can be appreciated by by my
fellow subscribers
but seeing what's happening in the west
i believe we are going to face this soon
or might already be in it be in it
from the big banner movies to tv series
from marvel to dc comics and even to
children's cartoons depicting men as
toxic
ruling over women ruthlessly since
ancient times the idea of women being
subjected to men's wishes is being
propagated heavily and quite directly
nowadays
not only this but also the futility of
religious values one's own culture
importance of family taking the
responsibilities are being looked down
upon i've spoken to lots of young people
from the west and they all seem to be
really comfortable in smoking drinking
abusing their parents and elders
glorifying depression and suicides
multiple partners expressing their
doubting their own sexuality from the
age of 13 which is hilarious and so on
how do these
narratives give power to the left
ideology
of group identity politics freedom of
expression and give a reason for
society's downfall
so the left has a very simple
strategy the strategy
is very simple at the core
break down the family system
because when you have a family system
you have people who can give you support
mental support who can take care of you
in your bad times and who can uh
influence you in a variety of ways
and whose influence is stronger than the
influence of the media and advertisement
advertising and your professors and all
that if you have a strong
family system if you have a strong
culture if you have strong attachment to
your culture to your traditional values
to your civilization to your family to
your extended family then you have a
very stable support system you will not
feel lost and you will not be successful
susceptible to being influenced strongly
and swayed this way in that way by the
media
by advertising and so on
so to make people vulnerable and
susceptible to any
messaging you want to give them you have
to first make them rootless
so
go after traditional values go after the
family system and how do you go after
the family system say that it's
patriarchal it is oppressive
men have been oppressing women for tens
of thousands of years so the family
system is patriarchal
destroy the family
let's uh let's not have family let's
have single parent families where only
the mother is raising a child or only a
father is raising a child let's have
broken families let's have
let's get divorced all the time in the
west that's what's happening
and uh attack traditional values so in
the west the traditional values have
been christian values which we know what
the story is
so even that gave people us a framework
a cultural framework that they could
rely upon for their moral framework for
their further
for their morality and ethics so now
that is gone
right
so men are depicted as toxic fathers are
evil men are bad
then question your sexuality become i
mean i'm not saying lgbtq doesn't exist
or whatever we've we know in india that
we have had that for
transsexuals etc for thousands of years
and they were never persecuted they were
only persecuted in the west
but now people are encouraged to
go in that direction so that there will
be no families
so what the main strategy is is to
destroy the family system destroy all
traditional values
make people completely rootless make the
individual the unit of society
not the family the unit of society
in indo-european society in all
traditional societies
the family
is the unit of society not the
individual historically it has always
been the family
and in a place like india it's always
been extended families not nuclear
families so now in india we are already
seeing the destruction of the extended
family
and the rise of the nuclear family
husband and wife father and mother and
one or two children that's what we are
seeing in the west it's not even the
nuclear family anymore it's single
parent families and lots of uh
ruthless individuals who don't even know
how many family members they may or may
not have
so they are
atomizing society they want society to
become
individualistic and that's all that's
always been part of the anglo-saxon
culture i mean if you see the way the
english-speaking world treats its elders
it is deplorable there is no respect for
elders
in europe in the non-english speaking
world there is a much higher sense of
respect to elderly people
in asia in india china japan etc it's a
whole different level of respect for
elderly people for elder people if
someone is even five years older than
you you treat them with deference
courtesy and respect that is traditional
values in asia in in the east
you don't see that in the
english-speaking world so their value
system has already been has always been
this way and now they are exporting it
worldwide you can see that in their
culture in the movies and so on so the
overall aim
is to atomize society destroy all
traditional values destroy the family
make every individual
alone
rootless
and vulnerable so if you are completely
alone if you are completely rootless if
you have no support system you are very
you can be very easily influenced by
your professors by the mass media by the
news media whatever they tell you you'll
believe and then they make you dependent
on drugs
on pharmaceuticals
and if you look at the us everybody
takes prescription medicines no matter
how healthy they may be
everybody pops pills every day like
multiple times a day in india no one
does that
but they would like that to happen in
india as well and then you have the
opioid crisis and all
so you consume this you consume that
everything is regulated by chemicals
and then you have then they glorify
depression everything is about mental
mental illness mental illness i have
never seen mental illness i'm not saying
it doesn't exist but the prevalence of
mental illness is extremely low in a
country like india
it's extremely high in a country like
the us depression mental illness
suicides
even kids are affected by this
so it's a terrible terrible society
they're constructing and it is very
dangerous for the world i spoke about
this horrific movie i watched batman my
goodness they glorify all that it is so
dark and depressing and some people are
saying abhijit you are wrong it has a
positive meaning are a baba what are you
talking about
so i totally disagree with this nonsense
that that this batman movie had some
positive messaging it was totally
negative totally nihilistic i'm not some
people are even saying nihilism is good
by what world are you living in
so anyway that's what it is so the
objective is to atomize and destroy
society to
make each individual
rootless
direction less
supportless and vulnerable
so that is actually what the objective
is and what it serves is it serves the
big industries so if if a person is so
vulnerable and susceptible to all kinds
of messaging you can make them buy
whatever they want to make them buy
so it what it's what it serves is it
serves
capitalism
capitalism is about using each indiv
each individual of the society is a
consumer
now if you have a good stable system you
will not want to consume that much but
if you are completely hopeless rootless
and alone
then you will feel that consumption
is going to make me happy
buy this buy that buy the newest phone
every year buy a phone every year then
throw the old phone buy a new device
every year buy the latest fashion look
at me do i wear latest fashion
i don't
but yeah buy expensive clothes buy
expensive sneakers buy expensive watches
buy expensive devices and your device of
last year is old now get a new one so
it's if you are all alone if you have
nobody to give you good advice you're
gonna keep consuming consuming consuming
and they can keep making money of you so
this so-called left ideology leftist
ideology it actually serves consumerism
it serves capitalism capitalism is all
about pursuing endless profits
quarter upon quarter profits how do you
make these profits how do you do these
profits by exploiting the planet
you cannot have infinite growth on a
finite planet why is the planet being
destroyed because of this infinite
pursuit of capitalist growth it is
capitalism that is destroying the planet
i'm not saying saying that we need to go
to maxism or communism that is also
equally bad
but it is this capitalist ideology that
has co-opted the so-called leftist
movement
and that's why we are seeing all this in
the united states and in the western
world
so uh that is something india needs to
be very careful about
okay so um gunpot says you mentioned
earlier that when india reaches the 10
trillion dollar mark
then india can have a big impact in
jio politics
uh my question is if we consider the
current rate of growth in the political
situation then will when will india
become a 10 trillion economy
is the government really looking forward
to that and uh are we on the right path
and so on look it's a simple question of
some mathematical calculations let me
show you
let me share something that i looked
into where is it
one second
let's look at gdp project projections
based on simple calculations
it's an excel sheet let's make it larger
[Music]
so we have this
excel sheet here
so we are at year 0 our economy is three
trillion dollars
and let's say we are growing at only
five percent per year then it will take
us
even after 20 years
our economy will have reached 7.96
trillion dollars at the rate of five
percent growth per year so it is too
less for us okay
if we grow at seven percent per year
starting at three trillion dollars
then it will take us
18 years to reach the 10 trillion dollar
mark
if we grow at eight percent per year
then starting from three trillion
trillion dollars today it will take us
16 years to reach
the 10 trillion dollar mark
if we are growing at 10 per year it will
take us 13 years if we grow at 12 per
year it will take us 11 years to reach
the 10 trillion dollar mark
so what we are looking at
is about
is a journey of about 20 years two
decades within two decades if we do
things right we will reach the 10
trillion dollar mark we need to grow at
minimum seven percent per year ideally
10 or more
is the government doing it they are
doing their best for sure they are doing
whatever they can they have done lots of
things that is going to supercharge the
indian economy we now have the gst
earlier we had octroi which was stifling
the indian economy it was ensuring that
india's economy can never grow so octroi
is gone we have a gst
we have gst which is in enforce today
which has completely opened up the
economy now every state can trade with
each other and we can send goods anytime
we want anywhere we want there are no
delays
there are no bottlenecks so the economy
is working much much better now then we
have upi which has totally liberated the
people which has made transactions very
quick it has unified the economy into a
big big unified whole and there are so
many more things that we are doing we
are seeing that india has become the
number one uh country for unicorns every
year india has the most number of
unicorns that are coming up every year
and so on and so forth so india is on
the right path
lot a lot more reforms need to be
implemented it's not easy it's an
enormous country so it's not easy but
india is on the right path i think that
within 20 years we should be we should
have definitely crossed the 10 trillion
dollar mark the the trick
the real trick
is to ensure that there is
peace and stability in india for these
next two decades because you can only
have high growth
and stable growth when you are
in peace
when your country is peaceful if you are
fighting wars here and there your
economy will definitely suffer
so the trick for india is to ensure that
we remain at peace
with our neighbors for the next 20 years
if we can do that we are guaranteed i
guarantee that we will cross 10 trillion
trillion dollar marks within the next
two decades two decades is not a long
period of time right
so the real trick is not about growing
the economy and doing this thing or that
thing but about
ensuring that india remains peaceful and
you can only have peace
through strength
that's what it is
gihan says should a country adopt harsh
punishments for serious criminals like
the saudi arabia and uae have adopted or
not
well it depends it depends on your
culture and your society
i'm not justifying
harsh punishments
and i'm not passing any kind of judgment
on so and so culture on ex-culture or
white culture or zed culture
some cultures are
inherently peaceful
india's indigenous culture and
civilization is inherently peaceful
people don't have criminal tendencies on
average you have far fewer criminals in
india than compared to certain other
cultures that has been a historical
trend when the chinese travelers came to
india during the gupta empire they
remarked upon how lax the
the system of punishments was the death
penalty was unheard of and the policing
was never brutal and so on and yet india
was peaceful it's because of the kind of
culture we had during the mauryan times
when there was this time of time of
strife when you had invasions coming in
from the west and so on the system was a
little more
harsher
during the gupta period we had much more
stability and peace so the system was
much more gentle
in saudi arabia there is a certain kind
of culture and for that they need to
impose harsh punishments the similar
thing was seen in iraq during the time
of saddam hussein the country remained
very peaceful very stable but you had a
harsh regime that was implemented to
enforce that look at the west
look at the u.s look at their criminal
justice system it is brutal
it is brutal the american criminal
justice system is among the harshest in
the world they give children life
sentences to spend the whole of their
life the entirety of the rest of the
life inside a box
inside a concrete box that's the kind of
harsh brutal
system the americans have they have
death penalty in a variety of ways the
chinese have a very brutal system so it
depends on the character of your country
the kind of cultural
and civilizational ethos you have
if you are inherently peaceful you will
not need such harsh punishments
india historically
has culturally and traditionally and
civilization civilizationally being a
very civilized
peaceful
orderly country the criminality
incidence of criminality per capita is
among the lowest in the world even today
even today after the
barbaric history of the past 1000 years
so it depends
when you have a society that is
that is more violent you will need
harsher punishments
when you have a society that is
inherently peaceful
then you can have lacks punishments and
you will still have lower order when you
have a mixed society with one section
which is like this one section like that
you have to
apply these things judiciously so that's
all just that's how it is done in
general
and so that's that's the general answer
to your question
raj or she says can you please explain
the importance of india's soon to be
commissioned ins vikrant aircraft
carrier against aggressors
and how important aircraft carriers are
in a war why do so few countries possess
them well
very few countries possess aircraft
carriers because they are incredibly
expensive pieces of hardware
uh
an aircraft carrier like the ins vikrant
would cost approximately
three billion dollars on the lower scale
or five to six billion dollars on the
higher scale right the american aircraft
carriers all cost individually more than
10 billion dollars each that's an
incredibly high amount of money so most
countries can't afford to have that
secondly when you spend so much money on
a single ship
you are concentrating a lot of your
lethality
of your navy's lethality
and investment in one single ship
right
so if you have an aircraft carrier which
can let's say the indian aircraft
carriers can carry about 30 35 maybe 40
fighter planes
and it is a significant investment you
have done so it is a huge very lucrative
target for the enemies
and
so that's why aircraft carriers very few
countries want to have them because you
can
for the price of let's say one aircraft
carrier which is let's say let's say on
average five billion dollars
you could have ten ten
uh or or fifteen destroyers warships
a destroyer of warship on average a
medium-sized one would cost between 200
to 300 million dollars
so for the price tag of 5 billion
dollars you could have 25 such warships
which can be used in a variety of ways
and you can disperse them throughout
your territory instead of having just
one ship in one place
so for the same money you can get much
more lethality and much more distributed
lethality
similarly
if you have missile boats which
typically costs 30 to 50 million dollars
you can have much more many more missile
boats instead of one aircraft carrier so
you can distribute your lethality much
more if you have a submarine that costs
let's say on on the lower scale a
hundred million dollars you could
acquire 50 submarines
invisible deadly submarines for the
price of a single aircraft carrier so
the cost benefit analysis is not quite
good when it comes to aircraft carriers
aircraft carriers are very nice to see
they are very prestigious ships if you
have an aircraft carrier in your in your
navy it gives you a great amount of
prestige but the aircraft carrier to
tell you the truth is obsolete i don't
understand india's obsession in the in
the indian navy's obsession with
aircraft carriers
when you have a war
with a well-armed adversary you actually
have to hide your aircraft carrier
why is it that in 1971
india had to hide the aircraft carrier
in visakhapatnam instead of instead of
i don't know if it was 71 or 65 one of
these two wars india had to essentially
hide their craft carrier because it was
vulnerable to submarines and what not
so it is very difficult to defend a ship
like that you need a whole ring
of other ships around it which will
provide the defense
and
so that costs
additional money so let's say the u.s
when it wants to defend an aircraft
carrier it has about 10 ships around it
which includes destroyers which includes
submarines as well
right
so it is very hard to defend an aircraft
carrier and it's a simple mathematical
thing you can overwhelm any defense
when you have more missiles than the
defense can
can cater for
so uh
so if you see my my discussion with dr
edward luther on on this channel
he tells very clearly he's he's one of
the greatest geopolitical analysts in
the world today
a great guy so he said very clearly that
the aircraft carrier was the capital
ship
of every navy every navy every navy has
a capital ship a great ship the greatest
of all ships so it used to be the
capital ship in 1945 in the second world
war
in the 21st century the real capital
ship
of of our navy is the submarine
submarines are invisible and they are
deadly they are very hard to detect they
can do far more damage
with torpedoes with missiles with cruise
missiles with ballistic missiles etc
than any aircraft carrier can do
so the real capital ship that india
needs to invest in
is the submarine
i just don't understand why we are still
in the 20th century mindset and i know
i'm this is not going to be popular lots
of people are going to disagree with me
well feel free to disagree this is how i
see it it is all based on the logic of
strategy on on the patterns that we are
seeing that we have witnessed in naval
warfare over centuries there is always a
certain ship in a certain era that is
the capital ship right now it is the
submarine the aircraft carrier is a big
huge target slow moving target very hard
to defend the submarine is the invisible
predator
that
that slinker slings around under unseen
undetected that is the deadliest ship
that india needs to
invest in so we are certainly investing
in a few submarines we should have many
more than what we have today so i would
say that please stop building more
aircraft carriers use the money to
acquire other ships especially
submarines we need to distribute our
lethality
instead of concentrating our lethality
right so i will go into the concept of
distributed lethality
in one of the future episodes because it
needs to be explained properly
but the importance of aircraft carriers
is ah
it's it's uh
these are not very important anymore
they actually have to be hidden
in in a real conflict aircraft carriers
can be used to intimidate small
opponents like that's what the us does
it is to project power and show that we
are the biggest
the biggest fish in the sea
but when there is a real conflict
between two equal powers the aircraft
carriers are going to be the first
casualties of war
so i think india should stop investing
in this incredibly expensive kind of
ship and use the money to acquire more
and more submarines deadly submarines
animish says what are your thoughts on
claims of russian military weapons and
equipments being being provided to india
as being junk
heavy maintenance corrupt lobby billing
for contracts
is israel a better and more reliable
defense weapons allied in russia and so
on so forth
i would totally disagree about this
claim that
several people make several reputed
defense analysts make about
russian equipments
and weapons being junk
let's take the mig-21 yeah we call it
the flying coffin today do you know that
this this aircraft first came out in the
1950s
and india acquired these weapons decades
ago these fly these fighter planes
mig-21s and they are still flying you
know why the mig-21s crash these days
because they are decades old there is
something called metal fatigue
but just imagine for so many decades
this plane kept flying reliably even
today
if you can make it fly properly it is
still a deadly fighter plane even today
it can still take out a f-16 plane
so that is not junk that is the very
opposite of junk look at the russian
submarines that we use the chakra
submarine
right
brilliant brilliant very hardy very
reliable weapon systems
excellent weapon systems we are using a
russian aircraft carrier which works
very well we have so much russian
hardware various anti-aircraft systems
the uh
s 400 for example is it junk no
the americans fear the s 400
look at the
the fox bat fighter plane f20 um sorry
mig
mig-25 was it i think that's the one it
was yeah so we had those fighter planes
those were
undetectable no they would they could be
detected but they could not be shut down
they were just too fast and they just
flew too high
so russian
equipment
is never the most advanced equipment
but actually it is the most reliable
equipment if you can get the spares and
if you do your maintenance properly it's
really reliable
and then you have these various heavy
duty aircraft sorry helicopters that
they make
again those are really really good
helicopters they can take a lot of
battering in warfare
you can shoot the helicopter with
machine guns ak-47s you can even fire
rpgs at these helicopters rocket purple
grenades and they will keep flying they
are built like tanks
sukhois
so you can take an engine out of a
sukhoi destroy an engine it will still
fly back to its base
so i would say that military equipment
from russia is excellent
it is never the most advanced equipment
but it is really reliable
these weapons these weapon systems are
usually built like tanks helicopters
planes etc the sukhoi sorry the the fox
bat fighter plane
was built from steel it was incredibly
heavy it could take any kind of uh
it could take a lot of uh damage and
still come back home
so that's
what i would say about it israel is
certainly a good partner israel is a
very good weapons industry very advanced
weapons industry and we are partnering
with israel when it comes to uh
to uavs unarmed
unmanned aerial vehicles
the heron drones we are also developing
the barak 8 missile defense system with
israel and various other things that may
not be
that well known so israel is certainly a
good partner we can certainly go ahead
and deepen our cooperation and
collaboration with israel
but russia is always going to be a
reliable partner it's it's had a very
long history of being a reliable partner
for us and a reliable supplier of high
quality defense defense equipment
so i would say that it's it's it's still
good
okay
uh dv says you said power trump's wealth
so how do you convince people to help
you for a greater cause
like shingis khan or chatham
even if the money isn't there
good question very interesting question
so when you look at the
life and career of ching is khan or
chhatrapati shivaji maharaj you can see
that the initial phase of their life was
was characterized by great suffering
great hardship and fighting as the
underdog against the greatest of odds
chingus khan
lost his father at a very young age
he was enslaved by his enemies he lost
everything he had all the money
everything and he was reduced to the
very bottom of the hierarchy of society
as a child as a boy as a young boy
and
he fought he clawed his way up from
there he realized that money is not
important it is power that is important
and he and he spent the first 30 40
years of his life just climbing up
to the to the higher position of society
he became a small
chieftain
of a small
tribe of people then he conquered
another tribe he defeated another tribe
and over the decades he'd eventually
step by step defeated
and absorbed all of the various tribes
of mongolia and he created a unified
mongolian nation he was able to do that
only in his mid 40s he was able to
achieve that
objective of unifying mongolia only when
he was in his mid-forties and that's
when he got the title of chinggis khan
the great ruler or the oceanic ruler so
how did this guy who had no money and no
support
convinced people to support him
similarly chatrapada shivaji maharaj
he had to fight a guerrilla war for
decades against the bomb monies against
the mughals you had to play one side
against the other he had to give up many
forts they need to reconquer these forts
they considered they they these mughals
these invaders the turks they
characterized
[Music]
as just some jungle brigand right that
sort of thing that's how they tried to
disparage him
and
play down his greatness but eventually
he was able to create what became the
genesis of the greatest empire in india
in the past 1000 years the great maratha
empire
so how did this guy with no money no
support do this
the story of ching's khan and shattered
shivaji maharaja has a great amount of
parallels so how does somebody with no
money
succeed
in getting support from people for a big
cause it's very simple
nothing succeeds
like success
you have to first show
that you are capable of succeeding
you have to first show that i am able to
bring together 10 people
and forge them into a fighting force and
succeed at a certain small scale
you do that 10 more people will join you
because you have shown demonstrated that
your leadership quality and you're
fighting for a good cause so now you
have 20 men instead of 10 men and you
achieve something bigger
then 100 people will join you and if you
keep on succeeding if you keep on being
a great leader and if you keep on
fighting for the right cause for a just
cause for the people
then the people will
slowly begin to notice you and they will
support you and you will gain more
support and with the support of lots of
people you will also get
financial support which will be useful
in acquiring procuring buying weapons
ammunition and all that and that's how
slowly slowly
the snowball effect happens the domino
effect happens
and if you are a really strong powerful
leader
if you have that thing inbuilt in you
then slowly from zero from literally
zero
over
two three decades you can build a
genuine
continent-sized movement you can do it
very few people have the ability to do
that do that
not everybody can be chatrapati maharaja
or chenggiskan
but that's how it's done so you can
convince people to help you if you can
demonstrate
that you are that you can succeed
nothing succeeds like success people
will follow you only after you show some
success
that's how it works
so that is the secret
uh general says how do we know that
pakistan we know that pakistan is a
nuclear-powered state
how will india engineer its
fragmentation
without pakistan nuking india
good question
do you guys
girls
remember the ussr
it used to be a superpower in the 20th
century the ussr
was it not a nuclear-powered state
it had more nuclear weapons in the than
the united states
was the united states not able to
engineer the fragmentation
of the ussr
without having a single
launch of a nuclear missile
they were able to engineer it without
firing a single shot
that's how
you engineer
the breakup and fragmentation of a
nuclear-powered state
that's how it's done
um
anime says most of the business books
authors whom i adore and admire are
posting on social media with severe
ukraine pro-ukraine bias and support
this makes me support the question their
ideology and authenticity now is this
just to gain popularity or their whole
identity is it flawed using their ideas
has given me success in my career and
yet i am here in a dilemma would you
recommend anything there
very good question i have a book here
this one here
this is the encyclopedia of bodybuilding
by arnold schwarzenegger i am a big fan
of arnold schwarzenegger i think he's a
very inspirational person
there's a there's a great deal that any
anybody can learn from the life
and career
of arnold schwarzenegger
he's somebody i have admired for years i
had enjoyed watching his movies and then
i admired his career as a bodybuilder
and the way he succeeded from no from
from essentially from scratch from zero
i admire arnold schwarzenegger for those
traits
i don't admire his politics
i don't support his politics and very
recently like in the last 48 hours he
put out this video on social media
supporting ukraine and it's an
anti-russia video and telling russia to
give up its terrible war and all that
right
so i don't agree with what he says
but it doesn't make me
dislike him and
dislike him now or hate him i still
admire him i simply disagree with his
political inclinations and his
world view about whatever is happening
in europe in ukraine
now we have to understand that he is a
u.s citizen now and there is a certain
mood a certain atmosphere that prevails
in the u.s
and if you express a certain kind of
opinion that is contrary
to the prevailing mood then you will be
cancelled
and people will stop you people will
demonize you people will start hating
you people may i don't know so there
will be serious consequences
so that's why he does it or maybe he
truly believes in it either way it
doesn't diminish
my admiration for arnold schwarzenegger
for what he has achieved in his life as
an individual right
uh
there is another person i admire a lot
dr edward luther i he was kind enough to
come on a podcast and have a
70-plus minute interaction discussion
with me
about india and china
very intelligent person great great guy
who he has done so much in his life
i really admire
his writings as a historian as a
strategist he is the grandfather of jio
strategy the godfather or the grand
master of jesus strategy
right
he was he was born in romania he is now
a u.s citizen
and if you look at
his
perspective on the on the ukraine war
it is once again very much anti-russia
very much pro-us and all that because
he's a u.s citizen it is his duty to
support his country
and all that it doesn't make me it
doesn't diminish my admiration for dr
edward luther any any
at all
right so the thing i'm trying to say is
this
there must be many business books
authors etc whom you admire and you
admire them for the ideas they have
given you the principles they have given
you in those business books that you
have been able to apply in your career
and maybe it has contributed to some
extent
to the growth of your career it has
given you success in your career
so that is something
you need to keep uh there is something
admirable
but just because those people have now
expressed certain opinions doesn't mean
you should stop admiring their business
knowledge
and whatever the whatever work they've
done you can disagree
with their political opinions with their
geopolitical opinions you can disagree
with them it doesn't mean that they are
no longer worthy of admiration for the
work they have done in business and for
the ideas they have given you
so i would say
that you should take good ideas from
wherever they come
if you get some good ideas from the
chinese communist party take them
if you get some good ideas from pakistan
take them
if you get a few good ideas from the u.s
take them use them implement them apply
them take good ideas take wisdom take
knowledge from wherever it comes
and you can even admire and respect your
enemies
it doesn't mean you have to like them
it doesn't mean that you should have a
soft spot for them
but you should certainly use whatever
knowledge
and whatever of value they can
contribute to you so that's what i would
say people have compulsions you live in
a certain country you have to say
certain things if you live in the west
right now you have to put a ukraine flag
on your twitter account facebook account
you have to say pro ukraine things and
anti-russia things otherwise you're
going to get cancelled it's a very
vicious culture they have in the west
they cancel people look at what they did
to j.k rowling
the writer of the harry potter books
they have cancelled her because she said
that women and men are different there
is a biological
gender is a biological thing it's not a
social construct that's all she said and
they canceled her for that
and the actors and actresses who who
played
who played the characters of her of her
that she created
they no longer talk to her apparently
and they don't even invite her for the
reunion of the movies and all that so
that's the kind of vicious culture they
have in the west
so people
no matter what their true
feelings are they have to
make certain public signaling and maybe
they truly believe it it doesn't mean
that you should not admire their work
anymore you should still
consume their content or whatever is of
value and you should still utilize that
in your career
okay sudan singh johan says there is
talk in the air about the chinese
foreign minister's visit to india
which is put forth which is the chinese
people which the chinese side has
proposed
it's a meeting to mend the relationship
between the two countries
give your insights
on this meeting from
various perspectives
and so on right okay
so i also heard about this that uh mr
wang yi the chinese foreign minister uh
wishes to visit india they have proposed
this and
maybe the visit will happen maybe this
this this month it's we are right now in
march 2022 so most likely it looks like
mr wangi will visit india on his
initiative
in march 22 or maybe in early april
early next month
and i don't know what the objective of
the meeting is maybe to mend the
relationship there is going to be a
brics uh summit in beijing later this
year so maybe he will also come and
extend the invitation to india's prime
minister for that thing
uh so that's
something
that's that could be on the agenda
now if they want to mend the
relationship between the two countries
we know the two countries india and
china don't have
a very good relationship we have a bad
history going back from the 1950s
onwards before the chinese communist
party came to power india and china had
brilliant relations excellent relations
china called india tianjin the center of
heaven
right so india was the western heaven
from the chinese perspective it's only
after the chinese annexation of tibet in
the 1950s that india and chinese
controlled territory had a common border
and that's where all the all the
problems started
and then you had the 1962 invasion of
india by the chinese
they captured parts of our territory
which they still control
and then there was the 1967 war that no
one knows about in which india defeated
china then you had the incidents in the
1980s late 1980s again in which india
defeated china and now the chinese are
claiming arunachal pradesh and so on so
forth there is this open border
and demarcated border and the border is
undemarcated not because india wants it
to be undemarcated because the chinese
are showing an extreme reluctance
to demarcate the border because they
want to keep pressurizing india and keep
india on the back foot
because there is an open border so they
can keep encroaching on
indian territory
so
i agree with with the chinese contention
that the relationship between the two
countries is not good
now the question is very simple
why is this relationship not good
who is the root cause
of the bad relationship
is it india
that has caused the bad relationship or
is it china that has caused the bad
relationship has india invaded ever any
chinese-controlled territory or is it
the chinese who have repeatedly invaded
indian territory it is clear
that the real problem of this bad
relationship is chinese actions chinese
aggression and chinese malified
intentions
and it is the chinese
who are
not amenable to demarcating the border
they are the ones who are showing the
extreme reluctance
so if
the chinese side wants to mend the
relationship
between china and india
i think it's very clear what they have
to do they have to take the initiative
they have to show the goodwill
the only
obstacle the only impediment
in achieving a better relationship
is the undemarcated border once the
border issue is settled
the entire problem will go away
so it is for the chinese
to show a willingness
to settle this issue the border issue in
let's say the next two years let's say
one year two years let's say five years
take your time but there is no progress
and they are the ones who are blocking
the progress
so if the chinese want to mend the
relationship they should stop lecturing
india that india should stop banning
chinese apps and india should open up a
chinese fdi
in india should allow the chinese to
invest in so-and-so sector no please
stop lecturing india if you want to mend
the bad relationship go to the root
cause of the bad relationship which is
created by you
china needs to address that once they
address this the relationship will
improve automatically
so that is what i have to say to this
chinese claim
that they want to mend the relationship
go ahead mend it it is up to you to do
that you are the ones who are preventing
the relationship from
from improving
okay a couple of questions about
saurashtra i live in saurashtra gujarat
i am a cartier i it is said that the
kathie's lived in sapta hindu or present
day punjab area of the time at the time
of alexander's invasion and they also
took part in the war against alexander
and dhruvik says
sara
sarastrin surastrini surashtra etc these
are some names by which modern subrash
region was referred to in history was it
sahara
earlier than relating to saurashtra
uh what is the history
what is the founding story of today's
katyawa region
okay let's look at the map where is
subrashtra kachevar
is the jaw of gujarat india if if
say india has a face the face is gujarat
right it looks like a human face
and the jaw this peninsula
is the saurashtra peninsula it is also
known as the katyavar peninsula
so it is named after the karti people
kathyavar
so uh what is the
so it is said that these people lived in
sindhu
present-day punjab well i have no idea
about that whether they the kathi people
migrated from
or punjab or whatever what we know is
that
the sindhu region
is
something that was highly populated
densely populated
for
according to the standards of those
times
about 5000 years before today so every
indian who lives in india today has
ancestry from those from that period of
time from that region right because
afterwards once the great reversal they
dried out people had to migrate from
sapta sindhu eastwards to various parts
of india
so it is clear that the people of
gujarat or the people of bangladesh
bengal
people of kashmir people of sri lanka
tamil etc
everybody has some ancestry from the
people who lived in the sindhu region 5
000 years ago
right that is undeniable and you can see
that in india's genetic studies also you
can see that
so uh the people of saurashtra the khati
people or whoever they are they will
certainly have ancestry from the sapta
sindhu region which is right next door i
mean saurashtra that region
was very much part
of the extended uh saraswati sindhu
civilization phase of india civilization
so certainly that would be there now
with the fight against alexander we
don't know about that there is no
evidence that says that the people of
saurashtra fought alexander
they may have but we don't know for sure
now what druik says is all these names
sarah ostus sirastrini surastrini etc
these are greek names indians don't use
greek names
these are names by which the modern
savage region was referred to in history
by foreigners we don't care what
foreigners say their perspective is a
foreign perspective
okay so uh saurashtra
most likely was
it's the origin of the name seems to be
saura rashtra which means solar land
so solar land means the people who
worship the sun
so that could be one of the origins of
uh the name of saurashtra either
rashtra which means the land of the sun
solar land or surashtra which means good
land a good country right so these are
two possible
origins etymological origins of the name
of this region savarashtra it is also
known that saurashtra was ruled by the
indus kitchens for a few centuries
uh people like rudra daman rudra sinha
etc
so the skittians were of indian origin
they lived in central asia for a few
thousand years then they re-entered
india about two thousand two hundred
years ago
and many of them settled down in western
india and their kings ruled these parts
of the country it is known that the
these kithyan kings the indus kitchen
kings the maha chatrapas
ruled western india including gujarat
and saurashtra for
a couple of centuries or so and they
were by all accounts very good kings
they were good indian kings dharmic
kings
and
the scitians
while they were in central asia
were known to be sun worshipers they
worshipped the sun
our persian brothers and sisters have
recorded this
that the sketchians were sun worshippers
and the sun obviously is a is a vedic
deity also so maybe after they settled
down in saurashtra and they ruled the
region for some time maybe that could be
one of the reasons why it was called
saurorashtra so these are some possible
origins
of the name of this region that's what
we can say apart from that our history
textbooks don't say too much more about
this
okay let's take one more question there
are lots more questions but as always
i'm running out of time so one more
question
this is by soham chatterjee
please help me please answer i am a high
school student i am not so good at math
i try every time but i score less than
less in 80s or even 70s
i fear that i might not be able to
pursue research in physics or computer
science things that i'm deeply
fascinated about
is there any way i can become good at
math again
please guide me i'm almost attributing
my failure to my to maybe my low iq
please help me so i think i have spoken
to you soham a couple of times on the
live video chat
i spoke with you you asked very
interesting questions
and i could not see any signs of low iq
in you i thought you were reasonably you
were quite bright the questions you
asked were very intelligent questions so
i don't see
i don't agree that you have low iq no
you don't
the thing about math is very simple
math is just logic
okay so if you want to learn math well
all you have to do is go back
maybe you're not
able to grasp certain
concepts of mathematics very well maybe
you're not good at algebra i'm just
guessing okay maybe you're not good at
algebra maybe you're not good at
trigonometry perhaps maybe you're not
good at integral or differential
calculus or differential equations i'm
just guessing
so how do you address these deficiencies
see mathematics is like a building you
have
a ground floor
you have a first floor second floor
third floor fourth floor fifth floor
sixth floor 20th floor 30th floor 50th
floor that sort of thing it's like
building a skyscraper
learning math is like building a
skyscraper
now if you are not doing well in algebra
or trigonometry or calculus or whatever
it means one of the foundations is weak
maybe the fourth floor is weak maybe the
fifth floor is weak so what you have to
do is to go back to the fundamentals
and master the fundamentals maybe you
should go back to arithmetic i'm just
giving an example
if you want to be good at math first
master arithmetic addition subtraction
multiplication division fractions
decimals all that
once you can do that very well once you
are really good at that which is very
easy it's just logic once you can do
that you will be good
at algebra
so then once you have mastered the
fundamentals of arithmetic start with
algebra and master the fundamentals
always start at the very basics the very
simple concepts if you follow that sort
of approach of going back to the very
basics revisiting the basics
mastering them
and then only then moving forward then
you will be able to master math easily
i think anybody can master mathematics
mathematics is the simplest and most
logical of all the sciences
it looks difficult because we are trying
to understand certain concepts
before mastering
the concepts that are at the root
of those advanced concepts
so that's all it is just go step by step
base
go back to mastering the basics
and it should work out fine and i would
suggest that you should
acquire some good
practice books
the only way to master mathematics is by
solving lots of problems hundreds of
problems maybe thousands of problems
that's the only way to master
mathematics so acquire maybe the showm
series books those are very good for
giving you all kinds of practice
problems so that's what i would say all
the best for him i don't think you're a
low iq person at all nobody is low iq
indians are the most intelligent people
in the world among all among all the
peoples in the world indians are the
ones who invented mathematics it is in
our blood
indians are the most intelligent people
in all the world so all the best soham
be confident go back to the basics and
you will be able to do well
all right with that my friends i come to
the end of today today's session
very interesting questions as always i
got so many questions i'm only able to
take a few but we will keep on doing
this keep asking me your questions my
dear friends and i will keep answering
them i will answer as many of them as i
can
every week
all right thank you so much
appreciate your support appreciate your
viewership and we will see we will meet
again next week thank you take care
bye